<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Theses Martinianae that is, certaine demonstratiue conclusions, sette downe and collected (as it should seeme) by that famous and renowmed clarke, the reuerend Martin Marprelate the great: seruing as a manifest and sufficient confutation of al that euer the Colledge of Catercaps with their whole band of clergie-priests, haue, or canbring [sic] for the defence of their ambitious and antichristian prelacie. Published and set foorthe as an after-birth of the noble gentleman himselfe, by a prety stripling of his, Martin Iunior, and dedicated by him to his good neame and nuncka, Maister Iohn Kankerbury: hovv the yongman [sic] came by them, the reader shall vunderstande sufficiently in the epilogue. In the meane time, vvhosoeuer can bring mee acquainted vvith my father, Ile bee bounde hee shall not loose his labour.</title>
            <author>Marprelate, Martin, pseud.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1589</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07040</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17457</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112312</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847567</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847567</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12605</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07040)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12605)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 433:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Theses Martinianae that is, certaine demonstratiue conclusions, sette downe and collected (as it should seeme) by that famous and renowmed clarke, the reuerend Martin Marprelate the great: seruing as a manifest and sufficient confutation of al that euer the Colledge of Catercaps with their whole band of clergie-priests, haue, or canbring [sic] for the defence of their ambitious and antichristian prelacie. Published and set foorthe as an after-birth of the noble gentleman himselfe, by a prety stripling of his, Martin Iunior, and dedicated by him to his good neame and nuncka, Maister Iohn Kankerbury: hovv the yongman [sic] came by them, the reader shall vunderstande sufficiently in the epilogue. In the meane time, vvhosoeuer can bring mee acquainted vvith my father, Ile bee bounde hee shall not loose his labour.</title>
                  <author>Marprelate, Martin, pseud.</author>
                  <author>Throckmorton, Job, 1545-1601, attributed name.</author>
                  <author>Penry, John, 1559-1593, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by John Hodgkins] by the assignes of Martin Iunior, without any priuiledge of the Catercaps,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Wolston, Warks.] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[22 July 1589]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Martin Junior = Martin Marprelate, who has been identified with John Penry and, more probably, with Job Throckmorton.</note>
                  <note>Often referred to as "Martin Junior".</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name from STC. Dated at end: Iuly 22. 1589.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Marprelate controversy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12605:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12605:1"/>
            <p>THESIS MARTINIANAE: That is, CERTAINE DEMONSTRATIVE Concluſions, ſette downe and collected (as it ſhould ſeeme) by that famous and renowmed Clarke, the reuerend Martin Marprelate the great: ſeruing as a manifeſt and ſufficient con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation of al that euer the Colledge of Cater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caps with their whole band of Clergie-prieſts, haue, or can bring for the defence of their am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious and Antichriſtian Prelacie.</p>
            <p>PVBLISHED AND SET FOORTH as an after-birth of the noble Gentleman himſelfe, by a prety ſtripling of his, MARTIN IVNIOR, and dedicated by him to his good neame and nuncka, Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Iohn Kankerbury:</hi> Hovv the yong man came by them, the Reader shall vnderſtande ſufficiently in the Epilogue, In the meane time, vvhoſoeuer can bring mee acquainted vvith my father, Ile bee bounde hee shall not looſe his labour.</p>
            <p>Printed by the aſsignes of Martin Iunior, without any pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledge of the Cater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caps.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:12605:2"/>
            <head>Martin Iunior ſonne vnto the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowmed and worthy <hi>Martin Marprelate</hi> the Great, to the Reader.</head>
            <p>THou ſhalt receiue (good Reader) before I ſet downe vnto thee anie thing of mine owne, certeyne of thoſe thinges of my fathers dooings which I found among his vnperfect papers: I haue not changed any thing in them, detracted any thing from them, nor ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnto them aught of mine owne, but as I found them, ſo I haue deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them vnto thee. Mine owne mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thou ſhalt vnderſtand at the latter ende in my Epilogue, to my nunckle Canturburie. This ſmall thing that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth before his Theſes, is alſo his owne. I haue ſet downe the ſpeach as I founde it, though vnperfect. One thing I am ſory for, that the ſpeach pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth the old man to be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing diſcouraged in his courſes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:12605:2"/>
            <head>THESES MARTINIANAE.</head>
            <p>I See my doings and my courſe miſliked of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny both the good and the bad, though alſo I haue fauourers of both ſortes. The Biſhops, and their traine, though they ſtumble at the cauſe, yet eſpecially, miſlike my maner of wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. Thoſe whom fooliſhly men call Puritanes, like of the matter I haue handled, but the forme they cannot brooke. So that herein I haue them both for mine aduerſaries. But nowe what if I ſhould take the courſe <gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈1 span left blank〉</desc>
               </gap> in certeine Theſes or concluſions, without inueighing againſt either perſon or cauſe? might I not then hope my doings woulde be alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether approoued of the one, and not ſo greatly ſcorned at by the other? Surely, otherwiſe they ſhould doe me great iniurie, and ſhewe, that they are thoſe who delight neither in heate nor colde, and ſo make me as weary in ſeeking howe to fitte them as the Biſhops are in labouring how to find me. The Biſhops I feare are paſt my cure, and it may be I was vnwiſe, in taking that charge vpon me: if that which I haue already done can do them any good, or any wiſe further the cauſe which I loue, I ſhall be glad, if not, what hope is there of amending them this way? The beſt is I know how to mend my ſelfe. For good leaue haue I to giue ouer my deſparate cure, and with this my farewell vnto them, I wiſh them a better Surgeon. Yet ere I leaue them, I do heere offer vnto the view of the world, ſome part of their monſtrous corruptions; in defence whereof, for their liues dare not they in any learned meeting or aſſembly diſpute with with me, or attempt to ouerthrowe mine aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by modeſt writings handled any thing ſcholer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like,
<pb facs="tcp:12605:3"/>that is, by good and ſounde ſyllogiſmes, which haue both their Maior and Minor, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by the worde. I woulde once ſee them enter into either of theſe courſes, for as yet they haue beene farre from both. Fire, and fagot, bands, and blowes, railing, and reuiling, are, and haue bene hitherto their common weapons, as for ſlandering &amp; lying, it is the greateſt piece of their holy profeſſion. And theſe with their bare aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; their wretched cleuing to popiſh abſurdities, are in a maner the onely proofes and tried max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imes they offer vnto the Church in this age. And ſo if a man woulde be confuted, I muſt needes ſay, my Lord of Wincheſter hath long agoe ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and dexterely performed it. <hi>I am not of opinion,</hi> (ſaith he) that, <hi>vna ſemper debet eſſe oeconomia Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae,</hi> That the gouernement of the Church ſhoulde alwayes, and in all places, bee one and the ſame, eſpecially by a company of Elders. Lo ſir, what ſay you to this? here is inough, I trowe, for any mans ſatisfaction, that biſhop Couper <hi>is not of opinion.</hi> Yea but our Sauior Chriſt his Apoſtles &amp; holy Martirs are of opinion, that the gouernment of the church ſhould alwayes, and in all places, be one, eſpecially by a company of Elders. As for my Lord of Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſters
<hi>opinion,</hi> wee haue little or nothing to doe with that: nor no great matter which ſide it leane to, whether with or againſt the trueth. For if his biſhopricke and vnruly iuriſdiction were no more noyſome and hurtfull to the Church of God, then his learning and opinion is hurtfull to the cauſe of Diſcipline, he might ſitte long enough vndiſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered in his chaire for vs: the good olde manne might cough his fill, and be quiet, hauing his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full<pb facs="tcp:12605:3"/>promiſe and booke-oth (as we haue alſo Iohn a Bridges and Bancrofts) that by arguments hee will neuer hurt vs. For they muſt thinke, that it is not ſuch drie blowes as this, <hi>I am not of opinion, &amp;c.</hi> that will ſatisfie the learned, and anſweare the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations that are brought on the contrarie ſide. If then they haue indeede any purpoſe at all, to quiet the contentions of our Church, let them bring vnto vs, not theſe bables of their owne, <hi>VVe are not of opinion, &amp;c.</hi> but ſome ſound warrant from the word, that Chriſt and his Apoſtles <hi>vvere not of opinion</hi> with vs in the pointes wherein wee truelie charge them to haue erred, otherwiſe their 812. their 1401.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <head>THESES MARTINIANAE: That is, The vnanſwerable Concluſions of MARTIN, wherein are plainely ſet downe many ſtraunge and vnknowen things (if here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after they may be prooued) againſt the Biſhops.</head>
            <byline>Compiled by Martin the Great: found and publiſhed by
<hi>Martin Iunior,</hi> for the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite of poſteritie, if his fathers ſhould be ſlaine.</byline>
            <p n="1">1 THat al the officers of a true &amp; lawful church gouernement in regarde of their offices, are members of the viſible bodie of Chriſt, which is the Church. Rom. 12.4,5. &amp;c. 1. Cor. 12.8,28.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That none but Chriſt alone is to ordeine the members of his bodie, to wit, of the Church: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb facs="tcp:12605:4"/>3 That the Lorde in his worde hath left the church perfect in all her members, which he ſhold nor haue done, if he had not ordeined all the offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, namely, the members thereof, and ſo hee ſhould leaue the building of his church vnperfect, and ſo it muſt continue, for who wil preſume to fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh that which hee hath left vndone in the build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Church.</p>
            <p n="4">4 That to ordeine a perfect and an vnchangea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble gouernement of the Church, is, a part of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes prerogatiue royall, and therfore cannot, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the great derogation of the Sonne of God; bee claimed by any Church or man.</p>
            <p n="5">5 That if Chriſt did not ordeine a Church-go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement, which at the pleaſure of man can not be changed, then hee is inferiour vnto Moſes, for the gouernment placed by him might no man to alter, and thereto might no man adde any thing. Heb. 3.2,3.</p>
            <p n="6">6 That the Lorde in the Newe Teſtament did appoint as perfite and vnchangeable a forme of Church-gouernement in the offices and officets thereof, as Moſes did in the olde.</p>
            <p n="7">7 That the Lorde neuer placed any offices in the Newe Teſtament, but the offices of Apoſtles, Prophets, Euangeliſtes, Paſtors, Doctours, Elders, and Deacons.</p>
            <p n="8">8 That vnto the end of the worlde there were no other offices to bee placed in the Church, but onely theſe.</p>
            <p n="9">9 That none of theſe were, and ſo no offices of a lawful Church-gouernement are to be remoued out of the Church, by any but by the Lorde Chriſt<pb facs="tcp:12605:4"/>himſelfe, who placed them, becauſe they are the members of his body, in the placing or diſplacing whereof, man hath no skill, nor yet commiſſion to deale.</p>
            <p n="10">10 That the Lord for the cauſes ſeeming good to his owne wiſedome (whereof any further then hee hath ſet downe in his worde man is not to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire) hath remoued out of the church the offices of Apoſtles, Prophets, and Euangeliſts.</p>
            <p n="11">11 That the want of theſe can bee no maime vnto the church, ſeeing the Lorde by remoouing them thence, ſheweth, that the body can haue no vſe of them.</p>
            <p n="12">12 That the church is nowe vnto the worldes end, to haue none other offices in it, but of paſtors, doctors, elders, and deacons.</p>
            <p n="13">13 That the diſplacing, or the want of theſe, is a maime vnto the church: And therefore.</p>
            <p n="14">14 That the churches of God in Denmarke, Saxony, Tygurium, &amp;c. wanting this gouernment by theſe offices, are to be accompted maimed and vnperfect.</p>
            <p n="15">15 That it is as good a reaſon, yea, and a farre better, to ſay, that learned men, and valiant cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, muſt haue their eyes put out, becauſe Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and Ziſca were blinde, as to auouch that the church of England may not bee gouerned by Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, Doctors, Elders, and deacons, becauſe other good churches want this regiment.</p>
            <p n="16">16 That to place others in the ſteade of theſe, is both a maiming and a deforming of the church.</p>
            <p n="17">17 That no magiſtrate may lawfully maime or deforme the body of Chriſt, which is the Church: And therefore.</p>
            <p n="18">
               <pb facs="tcp:12605:5"/>18 That no lawefull Church-gouernement is changeable at the pleaſure of the magiſtrate.</p>
            <p n="19">19 That the platforme of gouernement by Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, Doctors, Elders, and Deacons, was not deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by man, but by our Sauiour Chriſt himſelfe, the onely head, and alone vniuerſall Biſhop of his church, as it is ſet downe Rom. 12.4,5. Epheſ. 4.12. and 1. Cor. 12.8,28. God hath ordained, ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle.</p>
            <p n="20">20 That no inconuenience can poſſibly come vnto anie ſtate, by receiuing this gouernement.</p>
            <p n="21">21 That the true ſtabilitie of al chriſtian ſtates and common-wealths conſiſteth in the ſound exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of this church-gouernement, by Paſtors, Doctors, Elders, and Deacons.</p>
            <p n="22">22 That of neceſſitie all chriſtian Magiſtrates are bound to receiue this gouernment by Paſtors, Doctors, Elders, and Deacons, and to aboliſh al o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther church-gouernements.</p>
            <p n="23">23 That a church gouernement, being the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaunce of the magiſtrate, or of the church, is an vnlawfull church-gouernement.</p>
            <p n="24">24 That it is meerely and vtterly vnlawfull for anie man, church, or ſtate, to ordeine anie church-gouernement, or anie church officer, ſaue that go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement, and thoſe officers before named: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe.</p>
            <p n="25">25 That a church-gouernement conſiſting of any other officers, but Paſtors, Doctors, Elders, &amp; Deacons, is a gouernment of maimed and miſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen members: Therefore</p>
            <p n="26">26 That our church-gouernement in England by lord archbiſhops, and biſhops, is a gouernment of maimed, vnnaturall, and deformed members,<pb facs="tcp:12605:5"/>ſeruing for no vſe in the church of God: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alſo</p>
            <p n="27">27 That no lord biſhop is to be maintained in anie chriſtian common wealth.</p>
            <p n="28">28 That thoſe kingdomes and ſtates, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend any church-gouernement, ſaue this of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, Doctors, Elders, and Deacons, are in danger of vtter deſtruction, in as much as they defend the maime and deformitie of the church: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</p>
            <p n="29">29 That our lord archbiſhops and biſhops, in defending this their vngodly gouernment, are, not onelie traitours to God and his church, but vtter enemies vnto her Maieſtie, and the State, in as much as they enforce the Lord by theſe their ſins, to drawe the ſworde againſt vs to our vtter ruine.</p>
            <p n="30">30 That our lord archbiſhops &amp; biſhops holde it lawfull for our magiſtrates to maime or deforme the church.</p>
            <p n="31">31 That they holde Ieſus Chriſt to haue left behinde him, an vnperfite and a maimed church, wanting ſome of her members.</p>
            <p n="32">32 That they holde it lawful for the magiſtrate to aboliſh the true and naturall members of the body, and to attempt the making of newe by his owne inuention.</p>
            <p n="33">33 That they, to wit, archbiſhops and biſhops, are the maime of our church, and like to bee the deſtruction of our common-wealth.</p>
            <p n="34">34 That the warrant that the archbiſhops and biſhops haue for their places, can be no better then the warrant which the maintenaunce of the open and moſt monſtrous whoredome in the Stewes had in times paſt amongeſt vs. For by the worde<pb facs="tcp:12605:6"/>they are condemned to be the maime or deformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the church, or both. And as for the laws that maintaine them, being the wound and ſore of the church, they are no more to be accounted of, then the lawes mainteining the Stewes.</p>
            <p n="35">35 That the places of lord biſhops are neither warranted by the word of God, nor by anie lawfull humane conſtitutions.</p>
            <p n="36">36 That the gouernement of the church of England, by lord archbiſhops and biſhops, is not a church gouernement ſet downe in the worde, or which can be defended to be Gods ordinance.</p>
            <p n="37">37 That the gouernement of lord archbiſhops and biſhops is vnlawefull, notwithſtanding it bee mainteined, and in force by humane lawes and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances.</p>
            <p n="38">38 That the humane lawes mainteining them, are wicked, and vngodly, and to be abrogated of al chriſtian magiſtrates.</p>
            <p n="39">39 That to be a lord biſhop then is ſimplie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawefull in it ſelfe, that is, in reſpect of the office, though the man ſuſteining the ſame ſhould not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe it as our prelates do.</p>
            <p n="40">40 To be a lord biſhop in it ſelfe ſimplie, beſides the abuſe, conſiſteth of two monſtrous parts, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, neither ought to be in him that profeſſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a miniſter.</p>
            <p n="41">41 The firſt is, to beare an inequall and a lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſuperioritie ouer his brethren in the miniſtery, and the reſt of the church of God vnder his iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction.</p>
            <p n="42">42 The ſecond is, the ioyning of the ciuill Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracie vnto the Miniſterie.</p>
            <p>That both theſe partes are condemned by the<pb facs="tcp:12605:6"/>written word of God. Luke 22.25. 1. Pet. 5.1,2. Mat. 20.25. Marke 10.42. 1. Cor. 8.10. Luke 12.14. 2. Tim. 2.4. and Iohn 18.36. compared with, Matth. 10.25. Luke
16.13.</p>
            <p n="43">43 That the hierarchie of biſhops, in their ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perioritie ouer their brethren, and their ciuill offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces hath beene gaineſaide and withſtoode by the viſible church of God ſucceſſiuelie, and without intermiſſion for theſe almoſt 500. yeeres laſt paſt.</p>
            <p n="44">44 That this cauſe of ouerthrowing the ſtate of lorde biſhops, and bringing in the equalitie of Miniſters, is no new cauſe, but that which hath bin manie yeeres agoe helde and maintained, euen in the fire, by the holie martires of Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
            <p n="45">45 That this wicked gouernement of biſhops was an eſpeciall point, gaineſaid by the ſeruants of God, in the time of King Henrie the eight, and Q. Marie; and in the withſtanding whereof they di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the holie martires of Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
            <p n="46">46 That none euer defended this hierarchie of biſhops to be lawfull, but Papiſts, or ſuch as were infected with popiſh errors.</p>
            <p n="47">47 That we haue not expelled and baniſhed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie part of poperie, as long ae we maintaine L. biſhops and their ſeates.</p>
            <p n="48">48 That the offices of lord archbiſhops and bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, together with other their corruptions, are condemned by the doctrine of the church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</p>
            <p n="49">49 That the doctrine of the church of England condemning the places of lord biſhops, is approo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the ſtatutes of this kingdome, and her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties royall prerogatiue.</p>
            <p n="50">50 That to be a lord biſhop, is directlie againſt
<pb facs="tcp:12605:7"/>the ſtatute 13. Elizab. rightlie vnderſtoode, and flatlie condemned by her Maieſties royall priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
            <p n="51">51 That al her Maieſties louing ſubiects, Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters eſpeciallie, are bound by ſtatute (and haue the alowance of the doctrine of the church of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland publiſhed with her Maieſties prerogatiue) not to acknowledge, yea, to diſauow, and withſtand the places and callings of lord biſhops.</p>
            <p n="52">52 That the doctrine of the church of England in the dayes of King Henrie the eight was the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine which the bleſſed martires of Chriſt Ieſus M. Tindall M. D. Barnes, and M. Fryth taught them and deliuered vnto vs.</p>
            <p n="53">53 That this doctrine of theirs is now to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted the doctrine of the church of Englande, in as much as (being the doctrine of Chriſt &amp; his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles) it is publiſhed in print by Maſter Fox, and that by her Maieſtiies priuiledge.</p>
            <p n="54">54 That this their doctrine is mainteined by ſtatute, vnder the name of the doctrine of the faith and ſacraments.</p>
            <p n="55">55 That the doctrine which according to the word is publiſhed by Maiſter Fox in the booke of Martyres, ſeeing it is, <hi>cum priuilegio,</hi> is alſo to bee accompted the doctrine of faith and ſacramentes in the church of England, and ſo is approoued by ſtatute.</p>
            <p n="56">56 That vpon theſe former groundes wee may ſafely holde theſe concluſions following, and are thereby allowed by ſtatute, and her Maieſties pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue.</p>
            <p n="57">57 That by the doctrine of the church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, it is not poſſible, that naturally there can be<pb facs="tcp:12605:7"/>anie good lord biſhop, Maſter Tindalls practiſe for prelates. pag. 374.</p>
            <p n="58">58 That by the doctrine of the church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, a biſhoprike is a ſuperfluous honour, and a lewd libertie, ibid.</p>
            <p n="59">59 That by the doctrine of the church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, our biſhops are none of the Lordes annoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, but ſeruants of the beaſt.</p>
            <p n="60">60 That by the doctrine of the church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, our lord biſhops are none of Chriſts biſhops, but the Miniſters of Antichriſt.</p>
            <p n="61">61 That by the doctrine of the church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, our biſhops and their gouernement are no part of Chriſts kingdome, but are of the kingdome of this world.</p>
            <p n="62">62 That by the doctrine of the church of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, lord biſhops are a part of that body wherof Antichriſt is the head.</p>
            <p n="63">63 That by the doctrine of the church of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, the places of archbiſhops and biſhops are the ſeates of Antichriſt.</p>
            <p n="64">64 That by the doctrine of the church of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, a biſhop can haue no other lawfull autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, but onelie to preach the word.</p>
            <p n="65">65 That by the doctrine of the church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, the deſire of a biſhopricke, or anie other ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor in a miniſter, is a note of a falſe Prophet.</p>
            <p n="66">66 That according to the doctrine of the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che of Englande, all our biſhops and their chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leines are falſe prophets.</p>
            <p n="67">67 That the doctrine of the church of England concerning the ciuill offices of our Prelates, is, That all ciuil rule and dominion is by the word of God flatlie forbidden vnto the Cleargie.</p>
            <p n="68">
               <pb facs="tcp:12605:8"/>68 That according to the doctrine of the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che of England, the miniſterie and the magiſtracie cannot by the ordinance of God bee both in one perſon.</p>
            <p n="69">69 That by the doctrine of the church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, the ioyning together of the miniſterie in one perſon, doeth put euerie kingdome out of order.</p>
            <p n="70">70 That for a lord biſhoppe to bee of the priuie counſell in a kingdome, according to the doctrine of the church of England, is as profitable vnto the Realme, as the woolfe is to the lambes.</p>
            <p n="71">71 That biſhoppes ought to haue no priſons wherein to puniſh tranſgreſſors.</p>
            <p n="72">
               <note place="margin">Marke this (good Reader)</note>72 That according to the church of Englande, all Miniſters be of equall authoritie.</p>
            <p n="73">73 That according to the doctrine of the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che of England, thoſe Doctors (who are dayly al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged by our biſhops in the defence of their ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perioritie ouer their brethren) to wit, Cyprian, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom, Auguſtine, Chryſoſtome knewe of no autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie that one biſhop ſhoulde haue aboue another, neither thought, or once dreamed, that euer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie ſuch thing ſhould be.</p>
            <p n="74">74 That according to the doctrine of the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che of England, a biſhoppe and an elder, or a mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, note out in the word of God the one and the ſelfe ſame perſon and church-officer, the contrary whereof is popery.</p>
            <p n="75">75 That by the doctrine of the church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, it is popery to tranſlate the worde <hi>Presbyteros</hi> into Prieſt, and ſo to call the miniſters of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell Prieſts.</p>
            <p n="76">76 That according to the doctrine of the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che of Englande, D. Bancroft in his Sermon at<pb facs="tcp:12605:8"/>Paules the 28. of Ianuary
1588. mainteined a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh errour, in auouching, that in the dayes of Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian there was a difference betwene a biſhop and a prieſt or miniſter.</p>
            <p n="77">77 That according to the doctrine of the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che of England, Iohn Cant. is a mainteiner of a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh errour, in terming the miniſters of the Goſpel by the name of prieſts.</p>
            <p n="78">78 That according to the doctrine of the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che of England, our prelates haue no authoritie to make miniſters, or to proceede to anie eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call cenſure.</p>
            <p n="79">79 That by the doctrine of the church of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glande, to haue a biſhops licence to preach, is the very marke of the beaſt Antichriſt.</p>
            <p n="80">80 That by the doctrine of the church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, the godly miniſters ought to ordeine thoſe that would enter into that function, without anie leaue of the Prelats, &amp; not ſo much as once to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them to take anie approbation of the Prelats.</p>
            <p n="81">81 That according to the doctrine of the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che of England, there ought to be no other maner of eccleſiaſticall cenſure, but that which is noted, Matth. 18.15,17. which is, to proceede from a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uat admonition to one or two witneſſes, &amp; thence to the church, that is, not to one, but vnto the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours of the church, together with the whole congregation.</p>
            <p n="82">82 That according to the doctrine of our chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che, the citations, proceſſes, excommunications, &amp;c. of the Prelates, are neyther to be obeyed nor regarded.</p>
            <p n="83">83 That according vnto the doctrine of the church of England, men ought not to appeare in<pb facs="tcp:12605:9"/>their courtes, ſeeing their proceedings are ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly againſt the trueth, as now they are manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted to be, ſeeing the doctrine of the church war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranteth them no ſuch calling.</p>
            <p n="84">84 That according to the doctrine of the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che of England, that a man being excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by them, ought not to ſeeke any abſolution at their hands.</p>
            <p n="85">85 That according vnto the doctrine of the church of Englande, euery miniſter is bounde to preach the Goſpell, notwithſtanding the inhibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the biſhops.</p>
            <p n="86">86 That according vnto the doctrine of the church of England, a man being once made a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, is not to be kept backe from preaching, by the inhibition of any creature.</p>
            <p n="87">87 That according vnto the doctrine of our church, our prelates notably profane the cenſure of the church, by ſending them out againſt thoſe, who are not offendours againſt God, for money matters, and other trifles, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="88">88 That according vnto the doctrine of the church of England, it is great tyrannie in them, to ſummon and cite poore men, as they doe, to come before them, for hearing the word, or ſpeaking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their hierarchie.</p>
            <p n="89">89 That it is tyrannie by the doctrine of the church of England, and the badge of Antichriſts diſciples, for our prelates to breake vp into mens conſciences, to compell them by othes, to teſtifie againſt themſelues.</p>
            <p n="90">90 That by the doctrine of the church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, our prelates learned this abomination of Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late Matth. 26.93.</p>
            <p n="91">
               <pb facs="tcp:12605:9"/>91 That according vnto the doctrine of the church of England, none ought to be in the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie, but ſuch as are able to preach.</p>
            <p n="92">92 That according vnto the doctrine of the church of England, Nonreſidents, and pluralities of benefices, are moſt intollerable in the ſight of God and man.</p>
            <p n="93">93 That all true ſubiects haue better warrant to denie the ſuperioritie of biſhoppes, then the bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops haue to impoſe themſelues vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the church.</p>
            <p n="94">94 That her Maieſties true ſubiects in oppug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſtate of L. biſhops haue the warrant of the word of God, the warrant of our laws and ſtatutes, the doctrine of the church of England, the conſent of the church of God for the ſpace of aboue 400. yeeres, and her Maieſties priuiledge.</p>
            <p n="95">95 That the biſhops haue nothing for their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, but the corruption receiued into our church contrary vnto the word, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary vnto our ſtatutes, contrary vnto her Maieſties priuiledge, contrarie vnto the doctrine of our church.</p>
            <p n="96">96 That our biſhoppes in this controuerſie for their hierarchie, haue not me, poore man, for their onelie aduerſarie, but our ſauiour Chriſt, his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and holy Martires, our lawes and ſtatutes, her Maieſties priuiledges, and the doctrine of our church hath long agoe condemned them for trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors vnto God, vnto his word, his church, and vnto our lawes and priuiledges.</p>
            <p n="97">97 That Maiſter Thomas Cartwright, together with all thoſe learned men, and my ſelfe alſo that haue written againſt the ſtate of the Clargy, could do no leſſe then we haue done, except wee woulde betray the trueth of God, the lawes of this lande,<pb facs="tcp:12605:10"/>and the doctrine of our church.</p>
            <p n="98">98 That our magiſtrates in mainteining both the doctrine of our church, and alſo the hierarchie of our biſhops, mainteine twoo contrarie factions vnder their gouernement, which their wiſedomes knowe to be dangerous.</p>
            <p n="99">99 That this faction is likely to continue vntill eyther of the parties giue ouer.</p>
            <p n="100">100 That thoſe who defend the doctrine of our church in oppugning of our biſhops, neyther can nor wil giue ouer the cauſe, in as much as it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by the word profeſſed in our church allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by our ſtatutes, and mainteined by her Maieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties priuiledge.</p>
            <p n="101">101 That the biſhops will not giue ouer, in any likelihoode to die for it, as long as the ſtate will mainteine them.</p>
            <p n="102">102 That the continuance of theſe contrarie factions, is likely in a while to become very daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous vnto our ſtate, as their wiſedomes, who are magiſtrates doe well know and perceiue.</p>
            <p n="103">103 That their wiſedomes then are bounde, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen for the quieting of our outward ſtate, to putte downe eyther the doctrine of our Church, or the corruption, viz. our biſhoppes, and their procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings.</p>
            <p n="104">104 That they cannot, without the endaunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of themſelues, vnder the wrath of God, and the odious and moſt monſtrous ſinne of ineuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Apoſtacie from the trueth, put downe, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſh the doctrine of our church.</p>
            <p n="105">105 That they can not any longer mainteine the corruptions of our church, namely, archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and biſhops, without the ſhamefull contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction<pb facs="tcp:12605:10"/>of our doctrine, and the diſcontentednes of their ſubiects.</p>
            <p n="106">106 That all Miniſters are bound by ſubſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by vertue of the ſtatute that requireth their ſubſcription vnto the doctrine of faith and ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the church of Englande, to diſauowe the hierarchie of biſhops.</p>
            <p n="107">107 That it were well, that all theſe miniſters who are vrged to ſubſcribe would require a reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in this poynt, before they yeelde their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription.</p>
            <p n="108">108 That Doctour Bancroft in affirming her Maieſtie to be a pettie pope in his Sermon prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched at Paules the ninth of Februarie 1588. prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched treaſon againſt her Maieſties royall crowne and dignitie.<note place="margin">Pag. 68. lin. 19</note>
            </p>
            <p n="109">109 That the ſayde Bancroft is a traytor, in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming, her Maieſtie to vſurpe that authoritie within her dominions, in cauſes eccleſiaſticall which the pope vſurped in times paſt.</p>
            <p n="110">110 That our biſhoppes in ſuffering the ſayde Sermon to be publiſhed in print, conteining the former points of treaſon, are acceſſary vnto Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crofts treaſon.</p>
            <p>That our prelates. Heere the father lefte his writings vnperfite, and thus perfitely beginnes the ſonne.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="epilogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:12605:11"/>
            <head>Martin Iuniors Epilogue. To the worſhipfull his very good neame, Maiſter Iohn Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turburie.</head>
            <p>AFter my harty commendations vnto your VVorshippe, (good nunckle Canturbury) truſting, that you, vvith the reſt of the Cater-caps are as neere your ouerthrovve, as Jyour poore nephevv am from vvishing the proſperitie of your Antichriſtian callings. The cauſe of my vvriting vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you at this inſtant, is, to let you vnderstand, firſt, that I vvas ſomevvhat merry at the making heereof, being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſory, together vvith others of my brethren, that vvee cannot heare from our good father, Maister Martin Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prelate, that good &amp; learned diſcourſing brother of yours, but eſpecially grieued, that vve ſee not the vtter ſubuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of that vnhappy and peſtilent gouernement of L. Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops, at the helme vvhereof ye ſitte like a Pilate, or a Cai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phas rather. Moreouer, I do you to vveete, that you shal receiue by this bearer, certaine vnperfect vvritings of my fathers, praying your prelacie, if you can ſend mee, or any of my brethren any vvord of him, that you vvould returne vs an anſvvere vvith ſpeede.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12605:11"/>MAny flim flam tales goe abroad of him, but of certaintie nothing can be heard, in as much as he keepeth him ſelfe ſecrete from all his ſonnes. Some thinke, that hee is euen nowe employed in your buſineſſe; and I thinke ſo too, my reaſon is, quoth Robert Some, becauſe it was for your ſakes and good, that hee firſt fell a ſtudying the Arte of Piſtle making: Others giue out, that in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of his countrey, and her Maieſties, he died, or was in great danger at the Groine. And the others (ka mine vncka Bridges) haue ſeene motiues in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing them to be of this minde: Some there are alſo, who feare that you haue him in your handes. Howſoeuer it be ſomewhat is not well, that hee is ſilent all this while. We his ſonnes muſt needes be diſquieted, ſeeing wee can neither knowe where our father is, nor yet heare from him. If we could but heere by ſome Piſtle, though it were but of 20. ſheetes of paper, that he is well, we would not then be ſo inquiſitiue of him. But now that he hath bin ſo long time tongue-tied theſe foure or fiue mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths, wee muſt needes enquire of the matter. Speake then, good nuncles, haue you cloſly mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered the gentlman in ſome of your priſons? haue you ſtrangled him? haue you giuen him an Italian figge? or, what haue you done vnto him? haue you choaked him with a fat prebend or two? What? I trowe my father wil ſwallow downe no ſuch pilles. And he doe, I can tell he will ſoone purge away al the conſcience hee hath, and prooue a mad hinde ere he die. But tell me, I pray you, what you meane to doe vnto him if you haue him in holde? Do you meane to haue the keeping of him, leaſt he ſhould not be otherwiſe well looked vnto? whie what need<pb facs="tcp:12605:12"/>tat? I am ſure he hath 500. ſonnes in the lande, of good credit and abilitie, with whome hee might haue other gates welcome, then with any Cater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cap o them all. And I pray you, nunckles, neuer trouble your ſelues with the keeping of him, I truſt he ſhal do well, though he neuer come neere any of you all. And I thinke in reaſon it were more meete his ſonnes, then his brethren ſhoulde bee charged with him; if it ſo came to paſſe, that hee were forced to leane vnto others. This I knowe full well, that my father woulde bee ſory from his heart, to put you to any ſuch coſt, as you intend to bee at with him. A meaner houſe, and of leſſe ſtrength then the Tower, the Fleete, Newgate, or the Gate-houſe is, woulde ſerue him well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough: he is not of that ambitious vaine, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his brethren the biſhops are, in ſeeking for more coſtly houſes then euer his father built for him. And therefore, good ſweete neames nowe, if you haue him, let him bee diſpatched out of your hands, with honeſty and credit. My father is of a kingly nature I perceiue by him, hee woulde doe good vnto you, but he would not be recompenced for it againe. He will none of your courteſies vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it be for your owne ſakes, that you will giue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer your biſhopdomes, that is the greateſt bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite he accounts of from you, other recompence he ſeekes none.</p>
            <p>If you demaund of mee, where I founde this, the trueth is, it was taken vp (together with certaine other papers) beſides a buſh, where it had drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped from ſome body paſſing by that way. I hope my fathers worſhip will not bee oftended with me, for publiſhing of it, being not ſo perfit as queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe<pb facs="tcp:12605:12"/>he would haue had it. Hee, and you, can not but commend my good dealing, in ſetting it out; for I choſe rather to leaue the ſentences vnperfite then to adde any thing more then I found legible. The Arithmeticall nombers in the end of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amble ſhew, that when he had written ſo farre, he had ſomething more in his head then all men doe conceiue, which made him leaue in the middeſt of a period. I my ſelfe doe perceiue ſome tanto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logies in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſions as being the firſt draught, but I would not preſume to mend them, that I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre to himſelfe, if he be yet liuing, if dead, yet po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterities may haue his after-birth to be altogether his owne. And let them take this as his <hi>cygncam cantionem,</hi> viz. his farewell to booke-making. But that would I be ſorie of. For who can bee able to prooue the poynts which he hath ſet downe here, concerning the doctrine of our church, mainter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by ſtatur, &amp; her Maieſties priuiledge, ſo ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſo worthily, as he himſelfe would performe it. A thirtie or fortie of the firſt Concluſions are alreadie ſhewed in, Hai any work for the Cooper, and therefore they neede no further proofe then the reading ouer that woorthie Treatiſe, whence they ſeeme to haue beene collected. The reſt I hope ſhall be ſhewed in More worke for the Coo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</p>
            <p>And vather, if you can proue theſe thinges out of the doctrine of our church, then certainelie you deſerue to be chronicled for euer. Then Iohn Canturbury, come downe with thy poperie, ka M. Martin Iunior: for now art thou ſet out in thy co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors, to be an aduerſary, not onely of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, which all men might know, but euen<pb facs="tcp:12605:13"/>alſo an vtter enemie vnto the doctrine of the church of England ſowed heere by the holy Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tires, and ſealed with their blood, yea, allowed by ſtatute, and publiſhed with her Maieſties royall priuiledge, which is a point that the moſt haue not conſidered of. And who is hee now that dares perſwade Martin to giue ouer his courſe, vnleſſe the ſame alſo will ſhewe himſelfe an enemie to the doctrine of the church of England. For Martin in his writings, is not ſo much an ennemie vnto the biſhoppes, as a defender of the doctrine of our Churche. And therefore you Puritanes, that miſlike of him, take heede that you bee not founde amongeſt poſterities, to bee the betrayers of this doctrine (for your eaſe and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etneſſe ſake) which you are bound to deliuer vnto your children, without corruption or mangling, though it coſt you your liues a thouſande times<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For to tell you the trueth, if you do but read ouer the writings of M. Tindall, M. Frith, M. Barnes, M. Hooper, M. Knox, M. Lambert, &amp;c. which were the firſt planters of the Goſpell amongeſt vs, you ſhall find your ſelues in faithfulnes, courage and zeale, yea, euen the beſt of you farre behind them; which I ſpeake not but to your great ſhame, with a deſire of your amendement. And therefore I tell you true, I thinke it a great bleſſing of God that hath raiſed vppe this Martin, whome you can hardelie brooke, to holde tackling with the biſhops, that you may haue ſome time of breathing, or rather a time to gather courage and zeale, ioyned with knowledge, to ſet vpon theſe enemies of the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of our church, euen the doctrine of God, I meane maintained in our church. For that as hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto<pb facs="tcp:12605:13"/>ye haue done, you be ſo loth (for the diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing of our ſtate forſooth, and the offending of hir Maieſtie) not onely to ſpeake againſt, but euen vtterlie to reiect this hierarchie of our biſhops, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to haue no more to doe with it, then with the ſeate of the beaſt, you ſhall declare vnto our chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, that God raiſed vppe but a companie of whiteliuered ſouldiours, to teach the Goſpell in ſinceritie vnder her Maieſtie, and take heede leſt our forenamed fathers riſe vppe in iudgement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you. As for her Maieſtie, or the ſtate, I think ſhee hath little cauſe to thanke you for your wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, in ſeeking the quietneſſe of this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, by-winking at the ſinne of the pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pous miniſterie. And me thinkes you are bounde vnto her, and her people, to make ſo much at the leaſt knowen, as ſhee mainteineth publikelie in bookes, by her ſtatutes and priuiledges, to be the doctrine of this our church vnder her gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Therefore, looke vnto theſe thinges, for certainelie, if euer the Lorde ſhall make the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of our wicked biſhoppes knowen vnto her Maieſtie, to bee ſo contrarie to worde of God, the profeſſion of holie Martyres, and the doctrine of our church mainteined, both by our ſtatutes, and priuiledges, as in theſe Theſes they are ſette downe, aſſure your ſelfe, that ſhe will then enquire, whether ſhe had not any faithfull preachers in her kingdome, that would ſtand to the defence of the trueth, vntill ſhee ſawe further into it.</p>
            <p>As for the biſhops, they may herein ſee, to their woe, what wicked caytiffes they are, in maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelues &amp; their thrice curſſed popedome,<pb facs="tcp:12605:14"/>againſt ſuch cleare light. But the beaſtes, I feare, were borne to no other end, then to be the Lords ſcourge, to chaſtice his church, and then to bee burnt in hell. And out vppon them, they are as vnlike Chriſt, his Apoſtles, and holy Martyres, which were the planters of our Churche, as the wretches are like vnto themſelues. A man would haue thought, if they had not beene deſperate in their wickedneſſe, that by the warning which Martin gaue them, they woulde haue beene re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained from their villanie in ſome ſort. But, as though their very reaſon had bene cleane gone, the more they are threatned to haue their procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings diſplayed, the more wicked doe they mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt themſelues. As if they woulde declare vnto the worlde, that they will not bee made knowen vnto poſteritie, but vppon the condition, that they may bee the moſt wicked, that euer were in the church of God. They will be ſo many Iudaſes, ſo many Diotrepheſes, ſo many Simon Maguſes, as nowe they are wicked biſhoppes of Englande, or elſe they thinke not themſelues well dealte with. Wherefore, reuerend father, if you bee as yet on your feete, and haue eſcaped out of the danger of gunne ſhotte, beginne againe to play the man. Feare none of theſe beaſtes, theſe purſuvants, theſe Mar-Martins, theſe ſtage-players, theſe prelates, theſe popes, theſe diuels, and al they can do. Quit your ſelfe but as like a man as you haue doone in Hai any worke, and I doubt not but you will make theſe rogiſh prieſts lie in the kenell. The reporte abroad goeth, that you are drawen drie, and can ſay no more. They are fooles that ſo thinke, I ſay,<pb facs="tcp:12605:14"/>Let theſe Concluſions bee iudge, whereby I tell you true, I hope you ſhall be able to emprie eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie biſhopricke in Englande, if waight of tructh can doe it. There bee that affirme, the rimers and ſtage-players, to haue cleane putte you out of countenaunce, that you dare not againe ſhew your face. Alas poore haglers, their fathers are too yoong to outface the leaſt of your ſonnes. And I doe thinke, that, lay aſide their tyrannie, all the biſhops of Englande are too weake to deale with a ſcarre-crowe, that hath but the name of reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Martin written vppon it. And therefore, I perſwade my ſelfe, that they their ſelues are tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowlie ſo perſwaded, ka my nuncka Bridges, that you contemne ſuch kenell rakers, and ſcullions, as to their ſhame, in the time of your ſilence haue ſolde them ſelues for pence a peece, to be derided of come who ſo will, to ſee a companie of diſguiſed aſſes.</p>
            <p>Concerning Mar-martin, if he be a Londoner, or an vniuerſitie man, tenne to one but you ſhall ſee him, one of theſe odde dayes, carted out of the towne for his honeſtie of life. Why that time of his ſheweth, that hee had no other bringing vppe, then in a brothel-houſe. And heerein I woulde craue pardon of the vniuerſities, and the famous citie of London, if I ſhoulde bee thought to giue out, that ſuch a ribaulder as this is, were there maintained. To ſpeake what I doe thinke of the youth, I can not bee induced to thinke, that hee hath had his bringing vp at any other trade, then in carryeng long Meg of Weſtminſters hand-baſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, and in attending vppon ſome other of his auntes, at her appointment while ſhee liued. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:12605:15"/>her death, it may be he hath beene promoted vnto the ſeruice of ſome laundreſſe in a biſhoppes houſe, where, in hope to bee preferred by his good lordes, he hath vndertaken to mar-rimes, in publiſhing bawdery, and filthineſſe, for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of theſe honeſt biſhops.</p>
            <p>The ſtage-players, poore ſeelie hunger-ſtarued wretches, they haue not ſo much as an honeſt calling to liue in the common-wealth: And they, poore varlets, are ſo baſe minded, as at the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the veryeſt rogue in England, for one poore pennie, they will be glad on open ſtage to play the ignominious fooles, for an houre or two together. And therfore, poore rogues, they are not ſo much to be blamed, if being ſtage-players, that is, plaine rogues (ſaue onely for their liueries) they in the action of dealing againſt Maiſter Martin, haue got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten them many thouſande eie-witneſſes, of their witteleſſe and pittifull conceites. And in deede they are marueilous fitte vpholders of Lambehith palace, and the crowne of Canturburie. And therefore, menne ſhoulde not thinke of all other things, that they ſhould any wayes make Maiſter Martin, or his ſonnes to alter their courſe. And heereof, good Maiſter Canturburie, aſſure your ſelfe. Well, to growe to a point with you, if you haue any of your ſide, eyther in the Vniuerſities, or in your cathedrall Churches, or any where within the compaſſe of all the biſhopdomes you haue, that dare write, or diſpute againſt anie of theſe pointes ſette downe by my father, heere I do by theſe my writinges, caſt you downe the Gloue, in my fathers name, and the names of the reſt<pb facs="tcp:12605:15"/>of his ſonnes. If my father be gone, and none elſe of my brethren will vpholde the controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie againſt you, I my ſelfe will doe it. And take my challenge if you dare. By writing you may do it, qand be ſure to be anſwered. By diſputations, if you will appoint the place, with promiſe, that you will not deale <hi>vi &amp; armis,</hi> you ſhall be taken al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by me, if I thinke I may truſt you. Otherwiſe, the Puritanes will, I doubt not, maintaine the chalenge againſt you.</p>
            <p>But heere by the way, Iohn Canturbury, take an odde aduice of your poore nephew, and that is this. Firſt, in regard of your ſelfe, play not the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant as you doe, in Gods Church; if you goe on forward in this courſe, the ende will bee a wofull reckoning. Thou haſt beene raiſed vp out of the duſt, and euen from the very dounghill, to bee preſident of her Maieſties counſell, being of thy ſelfe, a man altogether vnmeet for any ſuch pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence, as neyther endued with any excellent naturall witte, nor yet with any great portion of learning. The Lorde hath paſſed by many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands in this land farre meeter for the place then is poore Iohn Whitgift. Well then, what if thou, hauing receiued ſo great bleſſings at the Lordes hand (beeing of all others in no compariſon anye thing neere the fitteſt for it, or the likelieſt to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine it) ſhalt now ſhew thy ſelfe vngratefull vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy mercifull Lorde God, or become a cruell perſecutour, and a tyrant in his church, a cruell oppreſſour of his children, ſhall not all that thou haſt receiued, be tourned vnto a curſſe vnto thee, euen into thine owne boſome? Yea verely. For
<pb facs="tcp:12605:16"/>the Lorde in one day is able to bring more ſhame vpon thee, and that in this life, then he hath hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped bleſſings vpon thee now for the ſpace of thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie yeeres and vpward. But when I doe conſider thy preheminence and promotion, I do ſenſiblie acknowledge it to be ioyned with a rare curſſe of God, euen ſuch a curſſe as very fewe (I will not ſay none) in Gods Church doe ſuſtaine. And that is thy wicked and Antichriſtian Prelacie. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of which popedome of thine maketh me thinke, that thy other place in the ciuill magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, being in it ſelfe a godly and a lawfull calling, is ſo become infectious, that it will be thy bane, both in this life, and in the life to come. And I am al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt fully perſwaded, that, that archbiſhopricke of thine, together with thy practiſes therein, ſhew verely, that the Lorde hath no part nor portion in that miſerabble, and deſperat caytiffe wicked Iohn Whitgift, the Pope of Lambehith. Leaue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore both thy popedome, and thy vngodly procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, or looke for a fearefull ende.</p>
            <p>My ſecond and laſt aduiſe is this in a word. Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer no more of theſe haggling and profane pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets to be publiſhed againſt Martin, and in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of thy hierarchie. Otherwiſe thou ſhalt but commend thy follie and ignorance vnto the world to be notorious. Mar-martin, Leonard Wright, Fregneuile, Dick Bancroft, Tom Blan. o Bedford, Kemp, Vnderhil, ſerue thee for no other vſe, but to worke thy ruine, and to bewray their owne ſhame, &amp; miſerable ignorance. Thus far of theſe matters.</p>
            <p>And mee thinkes you ſee, nunckle Canturbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, that though I bee but young, yet I beginne<pb facs="tcp:12605:16"/>prettily well to followe my fathers ſteppes; for I promiſe you, I am deceiued, vnleſſe I haue a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſmattering gift in this Piſtle-making, and I feare in a while I ſhall take a pride in it. I pray you, if you can, now I haue ſhewed you my minde, that you woulde be a meanes, that my vather, or my brethren be not offended with me for my preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this of mine owne head. I did all of a good meaning, to ſaue my fathers papers: and it would haue pitied your heart to ſee, how the poore pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers were raine and weather-beaten, euen truely in ſuch a ſort, as they coulde ſcant bee read to bee printed. There was neuer a drie threede in them. Theſe ſea-iourneys are pittifull I perceiue. One thing me thinkes my father ſhould like in me, and that is, my modeſtie, for I haue not preſumed, to publiſhe mine in as large a print or volume as my father doth his. Nay, I thinke it well, if I can drible out a Piſtle in octauo nowe and then. Farewell, good nuncle, and pay this bearer for the cariage. Iuly 22. 1589. With as great ſpeede as I might.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your worſhips nephew MARTIN IVNIOR.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
